בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is ז', zayin, and we
start at the top of the דף daf with a משנה. mishna.
And we're still dealing with issues relating to סכך, schach,
and now we turn to some of the classic issues that have
come up before. Here it is addressed in a משנה mishna and
directly in the גמרא, gemara, so hopefully this will clarify things. It's
in a way as a partner to the previous משנה, mishna, which
dealt with the extending wall, right? If you have a wall that's
ten טפחים, tefachim, it dealt with some of these sort of magic
principles, as I call them, לבוד, lavud, which is classic. If the
wall's within three טפחים tefachim of the ground, it's considered connected. But
then also if the wall's ten טפחים tefachim starting from the ground,
then you can imagine it extending all the way over up. גוד
אסיק, gud asik, excuse me, you know, extend the wall all the
way up, and even a position of רב יוסי Reb Yosi that
you could do it in the opposite direction. It could be a
suspended wall and you could say גוד אחית. gud achis. So those
are issues of לבוד lavud and extending the wall, גוד אחית, gud
achis, גוד אסיק. gud asik. This משנה mishna continues in that vein
with some basic principles of sort of the ways to extend the
wall and basic principles of what makes how the measures of סכך
פסול. sechach pasul So let's take a look. הרחיק את הסיכוך מן
הדופן שלושה טפחים. Harchik et hasichuch min hadafan shelosha tefachim.
If you distanced the סכך schach from the walls three טפחים. tefachim.
Now this is not the case of the previous משנה mishna that
there's a gap, you know, that the wall does not reach the
סכך schach from below. That, as we know, is okay. It's גוד
אסיק, gud asik, you extend the wall upward. This is a problem
not on the vertical plane but on the horizontal plane. The wall
goes all the way up to the top, but then at the
roof there's three טפחים tefachim of empty space before the סכך schach
begins. So that is פסולה, pesulah, that is invalid, okay?
So the basic simple example is if you've got here your סכך
schach and your wall down here, ten טפחים, tefachim,
you can make it go up. That's גוד אסיק. gud asik. Okay,
that's what we learned yesterday. But on the other hand, not just
like that. On the other hand, if what you have is not
that, but what you have is the wall goes all the way
up and your סכך schach starts here and there's three טפחים tefachim
over here that's empty space, okay, then it's not the issue of
the wall going up, it's the issue of closing that gap. And
the גוד אסיק gud asik isn't going to help you there, go
make the wall go up. If it's within three טפחים, tefachim, לבוד,
lavud, it's connected. More than three טפחים, tefachim, it's a gap, the
walls are not connected to the roof. And if the walls are
not connected to the roof, it's not a כשר kosher סוכה. sukkah.
Remind me why דופן עקומה dofen akuma doesn't apply?
Excellent question. Why doesn't דופן עקומה dofen akuma apply? So the answer
is, but then I want to it's a perfect segue to reading
רש"י, Rashi, is because דופן עקומה dofen akuma is when you have
פסול סכך. pasul schach. If that's פסול סכך, pasul schach, then even
up to four אמות amot it's a physical continuation. So we can
say it's a physical continuation of the wall. That would be דופן
עקומה dofen akuma and then you could do even up to four
אמות. amot. But you've got something. You can have something. So that
would allow you. But if you have nothing, then there's no thing
to consider the wall, there's only air and it's no good. Now
let's look at רש"י Rashi because there's some great רש"י Rashis on
this דף daf and this and let's and one here exactly deals
with sort of him considering an alternative interpretation and rejecting it based
on this משנה. mishna. So let's take a look. He says, the
רש"י Rashi I will tell you, let's
two lines from the top of the עמוד. amud. פסולה. pesulah. So
it says דאויר פוסל בשלושה אפילו מן הצד. de-avir poseil beshelosha afilu
min hatzad. Okay, because three טפחים tefachim even, you know, is invalid.
מן הצד, min hatzad, not אפילו. afilu. מן הצד, min hatzad, if
it's, you know, it's not a vertical plane it's a horizontal plane.
And then says רש"י, Rashi, ומכאן אני אומר ומפרש, umikan ani omer
umefaresh, and this משנה mishna is what motivates me to explain הא
דאמרינן ha de-amrinan שבסכך פסול מן הצד אמרינן דופן עקומה, shebaschach pasul
min hatzad amrinan dofen akuma, when do we say you bend the
wall when you have invalid סכך, schach you know, at the edge,
להכשיר עד ארבע אמות, lehachshir ad arba amot, to make it kosher
up to four cubits, היינו hainu the conceptual model is what a
bending wall means is דחשבינן לסכך כאילו מן הדופן. dechashvinan leschach ke'ilu
min hadofen. Like that that invalid סכך, schach, those metal bars like
I say, are like they're a bent part of the, they're part
of the wall. ונקף ונכפף למעלה, venekaf venichpaf lemala, and it's just
that the wall bended on top of the roof. ונכפף למעלה. venichpaf
lemala. ובאוירא ליכא למימר הכי, uve-avira leika lemeimar hachi, but if it
was air, you couldn't say the air is part of the wall.
But if it's metal bars, fine, it's a part of a wall
that has bent over. Okay, so what was the alternative to explain
דופן עקומה dofen akuma that I'm going to that he's rejecting?
ואיני מפרש, ve-eini mefaresh, but I don't explain that the term means
the following. רואין את הדופן כאילו הוא עוקם והולך תחת הסכך הפסול
ומגיע לסכך הכשר ומוציא את הפסול מן הסוכה. Roein et hadofen ke'ilu
hu okem veholech tachat haschach hapasul umagia laschach hakesher umotzi et hapasul
min hasukkah. I don't explain like that because... There's a very possible
alternate explanation of דופן עקומה, dofen akuma, right? גוד אסיק gud asik
what's גוד אסיק gud asik mean? גוד אסיק gud asik means like
the other sort of magic principle is you have the wall ten
טפחים tefachim and you envision it going higher. That's what גוד אסיק
gud asik means, right? So I could have said, says רש"י, Rashi,
that דופן עקומה dofen akuma means you have
your... That wall, there's nothing, there's air here, but you envision it
going through the air and extending. So maybe דופן עקומה Dofen Akumah
means you envision an invisible extension, right, through the air? Maybe you
don't need- maybe you don't need anything physical. Just you take the
wall and envision and you, you know, you- you imagine it extending.
Invisible wall. Right, an invisible wall. So the same way the invisible
wall goes up, maybe the invisible wall goes sideways? Okay, but רש״י
Rashi doesn't know- if he would have said that's what's happened, then
even with air it could have happened. So since we don't say
דופן עקומה Dofen Akumah with air, we only say דופן עקומה Dofen
Akumah with פסול סכך, Passul Sechach, says רש״י, Rashi, the idea is
not you envision the wall that exists to extend because then you
could extend it through with air. What it is is that you
envision the פסול סכך Passul Sechach as part of the wall. Okay,
so it's not the same conceptual model. This is you take the
existing wall and imagine it extending through air. This is you take-
not the- you don't extend the existing wall through air, you take
the פסול סכך Passul Sechach and see it as part of the
existing wall that's bent over.
'Cause פסול סכך Passul Sechach is certainly kosher for a wall.
Right. And if it were- and therefore, if it was only air,
you're stuck. Okay, so very interesting. רש״י Rashi explains two ways, which
one he adopts, then it's like fascinating. He's like reflecting on what
motivates, you know, why he chose one model over the other.
The- the פסול סכך Passul Sechach as an extension wall, then
what would be the- something- no, ארבע אמות. Arba Amot. ארבע אמות,
Arba Amot, right. Once you have שלשה טפחים, shlosha tefachim, it's not
connected. Air is a problem with שלשה טפחים. shlosha tefachim. פסול סכך,
Passul Sechach, you can bend the wall up to ארבע אמות. Arba
Amot. Okay, from the side. So that's- so that's that. Now, next
case, בית שנפחת וסיכך על גביו. Bayis sheniphchas vesichach al gabav.
A house had a- the roof crashed in and there's a hole
in the roof. Not the whole roof, the roof and there's a
hole in the roof,
and you put סכך schach, in that- in the hole in the
roof. אם יש מן הכותל לסיכוך ארבע אמות פסולה. Im yesh min
hakosel lesichuch arba amot pesulah. So there's a problem though. The part
of the roof that remains is invalid. Not necessarily invalid because it's
not made out of wood like kosher materials, but invalid because it
was your permanent roof. Okay, and you can't use your permanent roof
for your סכך. Sechach So therefore, it's the same- point. So same
הלכה. halacha. You've got kosher סכך Sechach. in the middle, פסול סכך
Passul Sechach around the sides, at the edges, right, the hole is
in the middle of the roof, that's where your kosher סכך Sechach
is. So if there is less- if there is ארבע אמות Arba
Amot or more of the roof, not of the new kosher סכך,
Sechach then you can't bend the wall that far and then it
is invalid. All right, so clear? It's basically another application of- you
get up to ארבע אמות Arba Amot of invalid סכך. Sechach, Oh,
not another application. It's the first application. The first one was just
the air. This is the principle of דופן עקומה. Dofen Akumah. I'm
sorry, what?
Around, ארבע אמות? Arba Amot?
Yes, six feet. Yeah. Yep. Okay. I jumped ahead actually because this
is the first application. I'm going to get three applications, this is
the first. So the first point is if there's air, air is
a problem even שלשה טפחים shlosha tefachim from the side 'cause you
can't say לבוד. Lavud. If it's פסול סכך Passul Sechach that's adjacent
to the walls, then you have up to ארבע אמות Arba Amot
to bend the wall. So that's one is the house with- the
middle of the roof falling in. וכן חצר שהיא מוקפת אכסדרה. Vechein
chatzer shehee mukefet achsadra. Let's say you have a courtyard that is
surrounded by a portico, I believe that's- that's the word for it.
It's basically like a colonnade with a roof on top, okay? So
now what did you do? You had here your- here's your courtyard,
right? And you've got these sort of columns, okay, going up, you
know, and you've got like a roof on top of your courtyard,
I mean whatever, you have like this thing- anyway, you got the
idea. You have this like portico, right? Okay, but what you want
to do is you're not going to use the existing sort of
roof of the- of the colonnade, of the portico for- for סוכה.
Sukkah. That's made for all the year. That's permanent. That's not kosher
סכך, Sechach. whatever material it's made out of. You want the middle
to be your סוכה. Sukkah. You want the courtyard to be your
סוכה. Sukkah. So you're going to extend your kosher סכך, Sechach, right,
over here. And can you use the middle to be your סוכה?
Sukkah? The only problem is is that their distance from the walls,
assuming you can use the columns as a wall, you know, let's
say they're within שלשה טפחים shlosha tefachim or whatever, so the distance
from the kosher סכך Sechach, to the wall is separated by the
existing rooftop, or let's say you got the back of your building
here, okay? So the back of the building is the wall. So
the problem is this separates that invalid סכך, Sechach not that it's
a bad material, but that it's- made as a permanent rooftop, the
סכך Sechach, from the walls. But if it's within ארבע אמות, Arba
Amot, you can imagine again the bending wall. It's another example of
the bending wall. Is that pretty clear? Okay, yeah.
If you put the kosher סכך Sechach over- over the top of
the פסול סכך? Passul Sechach? Right. Would that work as well?
Yes, I mean in theory... If you did it you could go
by the רוב rov principle. That's true.
But is it, are you allowed to do that with...
Well, that, right, according to תוספות, Tosafot, as long as there was
a little bit of an overlap it allowed you to consider the
רוב rov principle. So, you're right, you know, that would be something
you could consider that would negate these considerations, but it's how at
what extent you consider them to be mixed is a good point.
The תוספות Tosafot sounds like even a little overlap. Okay one minute
I just want to show a רש"י. Rashi. Okay so that's like,
so there's because again fascinating if you look at רש"י Rashi about
eight lines before the lines get wide you see where he says
the, you see the word at the end of the line where
it has like the hyphen, not the hyphen, the apostrophe in it,
or the quote mark in it. You see that word? You see
רש"י Rashi count one, two, three, four, eight. Right. Yeah, so take
a look, so look a little bit, so רש"י Rashi says, he
describes it, he describes the portico, and then he says דוגמא לדבר
dugma ledavar
comparable to this idea of this portico is what? So this is
the word, anybody guess want to guess what that word is?
Wait a minute,
wait a minute.
Cloister! Cloister! לשון אשכנז. Lashon Ashkenaz. So אומות umot of the other
nations, כן הגלחים ken hagallakhim the priests, okay, שיש להם לאוויר שיש
בה עשבים sheyesh lahem la-avir sheyesh bah asavim והקף אכסדרה סביב לו.
vehekef akhsadra saviv lo. They've got a nice courtyard with some grass
in the middle, and they've got like a, you know, portico surrounding
it, like if anybody was ever at UTS, Union Theological Seminary, I
don't know if anybody was ever there, anyway I once took a
class there, they've got that, you know, you walk, well, okay, yes,
a place that has something like that is JTS, you've got the
building surrounding a yard in the middle, and if you have a
walkway around that yard and it's a covered walkway, so there's, that's
a similar idea, and you want to put סכך Sechach on top
of it, okay, but I thought it was very interesting the reference
to cloisters and priests. Alright, so, okay, so that's scenario number two,
and now we have these are all essentially the same case. Scenario
number three is סוכה גדולה שהקיפוה בדבר שאין מסככין
בו.
sukkah gedolah
shehikifuha bedavar she'ein mesakh'khin bo. Simple case, you just have a large
סוכה sukkah and the edges of the סכך skhakh all adjacent to
the wall are invalid סכך skhakh all like metal bars. So אם
יש תחתיו ארבע אמות פסולה im yesh tachtav arba amot psulah if
it's four אמות amot from the kosher סכך skhakh to the wall,
if it's four אמות amot of פסול סכך, pasul skhakh, it's invalid.
All the same idea, two basic principles in this משנה. mishna. Number
one is that a gap on the horizontal plane from the סכך
skhakh to the wall of three טפחים tefachim or more is a
problem, you can't say לבוד, lavud, it's not connected. The other is
that if invalid סכך skhakh at the edge of the wall then
as long as it's at the edge you can bend the wall
and up to four אמות amot consider it all to be connected.
טוב יפה. tov yafeh.
I want to, I want to ask about application of רוב rov
where you have more kosher סכך skhakh on top of פסול? pasul.
Okay, yeah.
I'm going to bracket that question because that's not the topic of
this דף. daf. Okay? It was brought up, but it was a
topic of another דף, daf, you can hold it, we'll get to
it again, but it is not the topic of this דף. daf.
So let's take a look at the גמרא. gemara. כל
הני למה לי? kol hani lamma li? So why do we need,
thank you so much, three examples of the exact same case? Okay,
so צריכא tzrikha you need that דאי אשמעינן בית שנפחת de-i ashmeinan
bayit shenifchat if you gave me the case of the house that
the middle of the roof fell in, that you can bend the
wall, משום דהני מחיצות לבית עבידן mishum dehanni mechitzot labayit avidan because
you're using walls that are made for the interior. So you're, so
you know, you're starting with real walls, the walls of the house,
and then you're imagining them to bend. אבל חצר המוקפת אכסדרה aval
chatzer hamukkeffet akhsadra but in the case of the courtyard surrounded by
a portico, דמחיצות לאו לאכסדרה עבידי demechitzot lav la-akhsadra avidi what are
you using as the walls to your סוכה? sukkah? You're using the
back of the buildings, right, the buildings are sort of surround the
walkway, and the walls of the building are made for the interior
of the building, you're using the walls of the building for the
courtyard. So that's not really like a full wall for the courtyard.
So maybe that limits your ability to bend the wall.
צריכא tzrikha you need to tell me you can even do it
in that case. ואי אשמעינן הני תרתי ve-i ashmeinan hanni tarti if
you just gave me the case of the portico or of the
house, משום דסככן סכך כשר mishum desikhkhan skhakh kasher because although you
can't use the סכך, skhakh at least it's made of a kosher
material, right, at least if it's let's say it's made of wood
planks. So you can't use it because it wasn't put up for,
you know, it was put up for a permanent house, it wasn't,
so and that takes it out of the category of, it doesn't
have to be לשם סוכה leshem sukkah but it was enough לשם
צל leshem tzel but this was specifically put up to serve a
permanent, you know, a permanent purpose, it's like a בית, bayit, it's
not like a סוכה. sukkah. And therefore, that's what invalidates them, but
the material is fundamentally kosher, and maybe therefore that gives you greater
flexibility to be lenient with how much פסול סכך pasul skhakh you're
dealing with. אבל סוכה גדולה שהקיפוה בדבר שאין מסככין בו aval sukkah
gedolah shehikifuha bedavar she'ein mesakh'khin bo but if a large סוכה sukkah
that they surrounded it with something that we don't make סכך skhakh,
with... The edges of your סכך skhakh or all connected to your
walls are literally פסול pasul? material like metal bars, so in that
case, in that case, אימא לא, eima lo, that's a real more
serious invalidation of the סכך, sechach so maybe that I can't use
the trick of דופן עקומה dofen akuma to overcome that degree of
a problem. If the problem were only that it wasn't put up
for the right purpose, imagine it as a bending wall. But if
it's real פסול סכך, pasul sechach, maybe the bending wall idea won't
get me around that issue. צריכה, tzricha, you need to tell me
that. So all three cases told me whatever purpose the walls are
serving, however bad the סכך sechach, is, you can always do this
idea of bending the wall up to four אמות. amos. And again,
we have these really key principles. A vertical gap, excuse me, a
horizontal gap of air, שלשה טפחים, shlosha tfachim, you don't say לבוד,
lavud, they're not connected. If that gap is filled with פסול סכך,
pasul sechach, you can go up to four אמות amos and then
it's considered to be continuous or contiguous to the wall because you
imagine the wall as bending. All right? So those are the two
key principles of the משנה mishnah and now the גמרא gemara gets
to a very core question which we've touched on before but is
really not addressed in any משנה, mishnah, which is how much סכך
פסול sechach pasul is a problem in the middle of the סוכה?
sukkah? Right? How much סכך פסול sechach pasul would create a problem
if it were not at the edge but in the middle? So
let's take a look. רבה Rabba אשכחינהו ashkechinu לרבנן דבי רב. l'rabanan
d'vei Rav. Rabba found the rabbis, meaning the rabbinic students in Rav's
ישיבה. yeshiva. דיתבי וקאמרי, d'yasvi v'ka'amri, and they were sitting and saying:
אויר פוסל בשלשה. avir posel b'shlosha. Air is a problem with three
טפחים. tfachim. Wherever it occurs, at the edge, in the middle, air's
always a problem with three טפחים. tfachim. It breaks up the סוכה.
sukkah. It divides the סוכה. sukkah. סכך פסול פוסל בארבעה. sechach pasul
posel b'arba'ah. Invalid סכך sechach invalidates once you get four טפחים. tfachim.
So four טפחים tfachim in the edge you can go four אמות
amos and bend the wall. But somewhere in the middle, four טפחים
tfachim of פסול סכך pasul sechach already invalidates the סוכה. sukkah. Now,
let me say a word about what this means to invalidate, okay?
תוספות Tosafot has a nice discussion about this, but first let me
just illustrate. We assume you've got a סוכה sukkah of
three
walls, okay? I'll just draw like the aerial view of the סכך.
sechach We're assuming only a three-wall סוכה. sukkah. Four-wall סוכה, sukkah, a
lot of these problems would be solved, okay? And here you have
all of your כשר סכך.
kosher sechach. ואויר ve-avir שלשה shlosha is טפחים tfachim but ארבעה arba'ah
is אמות? amos?
No, ארבעה arba'ah is טפחים. tfachim.
Why? Why? Thought we just said...
No, it's because both in the feminine. It's... whatever, it's a modifier
of a masculine noun.
No, no. It's not the grammar that I'm asking about.
I thought אמות amos is מן הצד, min hatzad, not באמצע. ba'emtza.
We're dealing about באמצע.
ba'emtza. Okay. But באמצע ba'emtza is always טפחים. tfachim.
שלשה shlosha and ארבעה arba'ah is טפחים, tfachim, שלש shalosh and
ארבע arba is אמות. amos. It's the grammar.
But it's the same
thing, okay. Yeah. But as we said before, where it said before
that when you have
פסול סכך, pasul sechach, you have up until four אמות. amos.
That's from the side.
Yeah, from the side that you can bend the wall. At the
edge. Right. So yeah, I'm agreeing with you. I'm just saying the
way you know what the גמרא gemara is referring to is the
grammar. Got it. Okay, right. So here's the logic of why it's
a problem, of how it's a problem. If you have three טפחים
tfachim of a gap, right, of air, let's say here to the
side, you've got this gap. What it means is this סכך sechach.
is not connected to the wall, so you only have two walls
of your סוכה. sukkah. That's why the air invalidates. Let's say you
have three טפחים tfachim of air in the middle, okay? You've got
this gap in the middle. So what does that mean? Well, actually
this part doesn't have three walls, but this part actually does have
three walls, right? So you cut off this part. It's not connected.
But this part has three walls. So if this part is seven
by seven, you can still sit in this part of the סוכה,
sukkah, but you can't sit in that part, for they cut it
off. The idea is that it separates and it cuts it off.
So in that case, it wouldn't invalidate the whole סוכה. sukkah. Where
would it invalidate the whole סוכה? sukkah? Either if it was this
way,
okay? So if your three טפחים tfachim of air was that way,
so these two halves are not connected and each half only has
two walls. So air invalidates by separating the parts of the סוכה.
sukkah. You can't consider them connected. Similarly, סכך פסול sechach pasul invalidates
in the same way. It's not the presence of סכך פסול sechach
pasul labels this as a פסול סוכה. pasul sukkah. The presence of
סכך פסול sechach pasul, means you cannot combine what's on one side
of the סכך sechach with what's on the other side of the
סכך. sechach So if you have פסול סכך pasul sechach on the
side, you can't combine it because you bend the wall. But if
you have פסול סכך pasul sechach in the middle, like if here
was your פסול סכך, pasul sechach, right? Then you can't... then this
כשר סכך kosher sechach can't combine with that כשר סכך. kosher sechach.
So in this case, this part would be invalid. This part, if
it's seven by seven טפחים, tfachim, would still be valid.
The פסול pasul is not mixed together.
It's not mixed together. Right. And if it's mixed together, you go
by רוב. rov.
But if it's standing by itself, the air or the פסול סכך,
pasul sechach, or when it's like that...
you can't... one more time?
If you're sitting beneath the air or the פסול סכך, pasul sechach,
does that mean you're not in the סוכה? sukkah?
Yes, but it's even—right, correct. Once there's that much of a פסול
סכך, pasul sechach, it says that you're not—it's not—it's not a continuous
part of the סוכה. sukkah. Right.
But even if it's less than that...
So if it's less we'll talk about it, okay? If it's less
can you sit under it? That's a separate conversation. We're not up
to that yet. Okay, everybody understands זאת קתני zos kasani is if
three טפחים tefachim of פסול סכך, pasul sechach, can you sit under
it? So the answer actually to that is yes, but okay, we'll
get to that later. Okay, but if your פסול סכך pasul sechach
goes this way, it's the same issue. If it's four טפחים tefachim
you can't combine this half with that half, and each half only
has two walls. Okay? So that is the idea behind it. It
separates the halves of the סוכה. sukkah. This תוספות Tosafot spells it
out very beautifully. We won't read the תוספות Tosafot inside. The one
question תוספות Tosafot is left with is, let's say your אויר avir
or your פסול סכך pasul sechach doesn't go from wall to wall.
Let's say it's right here, a four by four טפחים tefachim section
in the middle, right? So תוספות Tosafot wants to know, right? He
says, if this part here is seven by seven and it's a
כשרה סוכה kosher sukkah before you even get to that problem, then
you have a כשרה סוכה kosher sukkah and everything else is an
extension of a כשרה סוכה kosher sukkah and it's fine. Okay? So
it's all okay. Maybe that would be you can't sit under that
open אויר avir space or that פסול סכך pasul sechach space, but
it's all an extension of a כשרה סוכה. kosher sukkah. But if
this part is not a כשרה סוכה, kosher sukkah, what do we
do with this? Do we sort of say yeah, but you know,
you still extend and you still have a שיעור shiur and you
just have a hole in the middle, and you still have a
כשרה סוכה, kosher sukkah, it doesn't break it up because it's not
going from side to side, or not? תוספות Tosafot is a little
uncertain. But the... What?
Would you say that of the wall also? If you have a
single wall
extension... Right.
Yes, you actually do. You actually say that. That's the principle of
פסל היוצא מן הסוכה. pasal hayotzei min hasukkah. If you have this,
a total כשרה סוכה, kosher sukkah, and then the סכך sechach. even
without any walls continues to extend, if you're sitting under this סכך,
sechach you're יוצא yotzei because you have... It's an extension of סכך
sechach, from what it begins as a כשרה סוכה. kosher sukkah. So
although it's an interesting question if the פסול סכך pasul sechach is
in a three by three or if it's אויר avir or four
by four segment in the middle, but the classic case is it
goes from one end to the other and it breaks up the
continuation of the סכך sechach and you have to chop it off
at that point, and then you... And then if what you're left
with is a כשרה סוכה, kosher sukkah, you can sit in that
half of it. But if what you're left with is two non-כשרות
סוכות, kosher sukkot, you don't have anything.
Is this why—is this why
we—if you have a metal frame supporting the סכך, sechach that's why
we put wooden boards on it?
No, that's a different issue, מעמיד. ma'amid. We'll get to that.
Yes, what if the tree branches also in terms of is it
כשר kasher but you just should not sit...
Right. So that's the other issue which דב Dov also raised. Is
if there's a middle stage where you could say it doesn't invalidate
the סוכה, sukkah, but you won't be able to sit under it.
So for example,
let's say it was—let's say you had תוספות's Tosafot cases of a
four by four טפח tefach פסול סכך pasul sechach in the center
or three by three אויר. avir. That would be a case where
you could say, okay, the סוכה sukkah extends around it, but that
space right there, that's a zone where it's not a continuous part
of the סוכה. sukkah. You can't sit in that directly under that
thing. Now if it's a smaller piece, and this happens all the
time with, you know, with decorations—we learned before if the decoration is
close to the סכך, sechach, they're part of the סכך, sechach, but
if they're low-hanging
decorations—so if it's smaller than four by four of a פסול סכך,
pasul sechach, or which is pretty small, which gives you a lot
of latitude, it's a foot by a foot, then it's okay. But
if it's four by four of פסול סכך pasul sechach or three
by three of אויר avir in the middle and it's not, you
know, it's a little square, then don't sit under it. Then you're
not sitting under the סוכה. sukkah. Let's say it's less than four
פסול, pasul three of פסול, pasul, then actually we would say because
we consider the סוכה sukkah as continuous,
the סכך sechach, as contiguous and it's one unit, you actually can
sit under—are allowed to sit under פסול סכך pasul sechach less than
four טפחים. tefachim. Okay? And that's... So that is a bit of
a shock, but yes, that's okay.
What?
Including some tree branches? Right, I mean people normally do the whole
thing, but yes. All right, anyway. So but we're not talking about
sitting under, we're talking about פוסל-ing posel the whole סוכה. sukkah. So
let's keep on reading. Okay? So it says like this. So he
says, so this is the ישיבה yeshiva students in רב's Rav house
were saying four טפחים tefachim of פסול סכך pasul sechach in the
middle. By the side you bend the wall, but in the middle
four
טפחים. tefachim. ואמינא להו אנא, va'amina lehu ana, and I, says רבה,
Rabba, said to them,
אויר דפוסל בשלושה מנא לכו, avir depasel bishlosha mena lachu, where do
you know this idea that אויר avir invalidates by three? דתנן, detnan,
you learned it from our משנה. mishna. הרחיק את הסיכוך מן הדפנות
שלושה טפחים פסולה. hirchik es hasichuch min hadafnos shlosha tefachim pesula. If
you distance on the horizontal plane the סכך sechach from the walls
three טפחים, tefachim, it's invalid. Okay, he said, סכך פסול נמי לא
לפסול אלא בארבע אמות. sechach pasul nami lo lifsol ela bearba amos.
So if the משנה mishna is your guide, the same way the
משנה mishna tells you three טפחים tefachim by אויר, avir, it should
tell you four אמות amos by פסול סכך pasul sechach even in
the middle. Even in the middle it shouldn't be a problem until
it's four אמות. amos. Now again, this would be a perfect example.
He wouldn't say you could sit under it. If it were two
אמות amos of פסול סכך pasul sechach in the middle you couldn't
sit under it, but... doesn't invalidate the סוכה. sukkah. It would still
be considered a contiguous סכך, sechach you know, and the סוכה sukkah
would not be broken in half. The same way it's three טפחים
tefachim of air in the משנה, Mishnah, it's also ארבע אמות, four
amot, and I don't see any difference between whether it's on the
side or in the middle. That's the amount you need in order
to break up the סוכה. sukkah. Okay, so he says...
okay... תנן, tenan, we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, בית שנפחת וסיכך
על גביו אם יש בין הסכך לכותל ארבע אמות פסולה. bayit shenifchat
vesichech al gabav im yesh bein haschach lakotel arba amot pesulah. Okay,
you see ארבע אמות four amot is what you need to be
a problem with פסול סכך. pasul schach. ואמרו לי, veamru li, and
they said back to me, בר מינה דהיא, bar minah dehi, no
forget that case, you know, exclude that case. דרב ושמואל דאמרי תרווייהו,
deRav uShmuel deamri tarvaihu, because Rav and Shmuel both say, and these
are Rava's students, משום דופן עקומה נגעו בה. mishum dofen akumah nagu
bah. That's a special idea of a bending wall, which is what
I've been telling you from the beginning. But the fascinating thing is
Rava doesn't believe in it. According to Rava, it seems there's no
principle of bending walls. There's a principle that anything less than ארבע
אמות four amot of פסול סכך pasul schach does not break up
the סכך schach, from the rest of the סוכה. sukkah. And if
you had ארבע אמות, four amot, according to Rava, if you had,
right, ארבע אמות four amot of פסול סכך pasul schach right here,
you had a huge פסול סכך pasul schach and it was 3.9
אמות, amot, right, you would still say, yeah, okay, don't sit under
it, but it's all considered connected. And the idea of 3.9 אמות
amot by the side isn't an idea of some magic bending wall.
It's just an idea that up to ארבע אמות four amot it's
all considered to be connected. Maybe don't sit under it, but it's
all considered to be one piece, it doesn't break up the סוכה.
sukkah. Okay, so that's what Rava says. Rava says I don't believe
in this bending wall. But Rav and Shmuel say, no, by the
side it's special. That's the idea of bending wall. In the middle,
even ארבעה טפחים arbaah tefachim breaks up the סוכה. sukkah. Okay, so
now we're going to get into a fascinating discussion, and before we
run to textual proof, what is fascinating is the גמרא Gemara first
deals with this and tries to argue this logically, which is lovely.
So let's take a look at this. So it says like this,
ואמינא להו אנא, vaamina lehu ana, so I said back to them,
מה אילו איכא סכך פסול פחות מארבעה, mah ilu ika schach pasul
pachot mearbaah, let's according to you, ארבעה טפחים arbaah tefachim is a
problem, right? Let's think of the following scenario. You had invalid סכך
schach less than ארבעה טפחים. arbaah tefachim. שלושה טפחים shloshah tefachim of
invalid סכך. schach ואוויר פחות משלושה, veavir pachot mishloshah, and right next
to it you had a gap of air, שני טפחים. shnei tefachim.
מה, mah, what would you say? כשרה, ksherah, you'd say it's kosher.
Okay, right here's the scenario, you've got,
right, I gotta get this to be a side view. You've got
your שני טפחים shnei tefachim of כשר סכך, kasher schach, a פסול
סכך, pasul schach, right here's your כשר, kasher,
oh I'm sorry, and here's your כשר, kasher, a gap, you have
שלושה טפחים shloshah tefachim of פסול סכך, pasul schach, right, and שני
טפחים shnei tefachim of air. Okay. Now that's כשר, kasher, right? Because
you don't have, this isn't שלושה טפחים, shloshah tefachim, שלושה טפחים shloshah
tefachim of air furthermore, and this isn't ארבעה טפחים. arbaah tefachim. Okay,
this is, okay, you see I'm just giving you a side view,
okay, but you got it?
You got five all together.
So he says, what would you say about that? They'd say, oh,
well we'd say that's כשר. kasher. So he says, okay,
so, מה, mah, you'd say כשרה. ksherah. מלאו בשפודים, milao beshpudim, if
you filled that air with metal bars, מה, mah, what would be
the הלכה? halacha? פסולה. psulah. If you went ahead and you took
this air and you filled it with metal bars, then you'd have
חמישה טפחים chamishah tefachim of פסול סכך, pasul schach, it would be
invalid. Okay, what's the problem with that? So he says, ולא יהא
אוויר הפוסל בשלושה כסכך פסול הפוסל בארבעה. velo yehei avir haposel bishloshah
keschach pasul haposel bearbaah. He says I don't get it. Which is
the stronger, which is the one that's more invalidates, air or פסול
סכך? pasul schach? Air. Because air invalidates with שלושה טפחים, shloshah tefachim,
and פסול סכך pasul schach invalidates with ארבעה טפחים. arbaah tefachim. So
air is a more powerful break, right? Remember by the idea, and
I'm sort of a little bit giving away where the גמרא Gemara
is going, conceptually, what does air do, what does פסול סכך pasul
schach do? They create a break between the two halves of the
סוכה, sukkah, right? If you can't say לבוד, lavud, then they're considered
broken from one another. If you have ארבעה טפחים arbaah tefachim of
פסול סכך, pasul schach, the two halves are like this, it's broken.
So he says, look, air is a bigger break than פסול סכך,
pasul schach, right? So if air breaks more easily than פסול סכך,
pasul schach, because air is three and פסול סכך pasul schach is
four, so then how could it be that these שני טפחים shnei
tefachim when they're filled with the weaker פסול סכך pasul schach create
a break, but when they're just air, which is a stronger break,
you say that that doesn't break the two halves? Okay, that's his
question. Now again, the answer could be because you say לבוד lavud
and it's like there's no air there. All right, that's the idea
of לבוד. lavud. But that's his question. If they both break the
סוכה, sukkah,
why should that not invalidate? שלושה shloshah of one and שניים shnayim
of the other? Air is a more stronger breaker of the two
halves of the סוכה. sukkah.
You could say that stuff and stuff is מצטרף. mitztaref.
Obviously. Okay, but let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this, ואמרו לי, veamru li, and they said back to me,
אי הכי, ei hachi, if that's true, that's your whole proof that
we're wrong, that it can't be ארבעה טפחים arbaah tefachim because of
this, you know, thought experiment? You could ask the same thought experiment
to you. לדידך נמי דאמרת סכך פסול פוסל בארבע אמות. le'didech nami
d'amrat sechach pasul posel b'arba amot. You say four אמות. amot. מה
אילו איכא סכך פסול פחות מארבע אמות והוו פחות משמונה מאי כשרה.
ma ilu ika sechach pasul pachot me'arba amot ve'havu pachot mishmoneh mai
kshira. Let's say you had, fine, we'll take your scenario, but instead
of three טפחים tefachim and two טפחים, tefachim, let's say you had,
you know, a lot of סכך פסול, sechach pasul you had 3.9
אמות, amot, right, and then you had, right, two טפחים? tefachim? So
that's כשר, kosher, right, because 3.9 אמות amot is not enough סכך
פסול schach pasul, and two טפחים tefachim is not enough air. And
then the, מאי הוי בשפודי מאי? mai havei beshipudei mai? But if
you filled those two טפחים tefachim of air with some metal bars,
what would be the הלכה? halacha? פסולה, psula, it'd be invalid. ולא
יהא אויר הפוסל בשלושה, v'lo yehei avir haposel bishlosha, so air which
is a stronger invalidator, even three טפחים tefachim invalidate, כסכך פסול הפוסל
בארבע, k'sechach pasul haposel b'arba, couldn't it be as strong as the
פסול סכך pasul sechach which is a much weaker invalidator? This question
you could ask on any approach. Why is it that this is
כשר kosher but if you filled this with סכך, schach. which is
a weaker invalidator, then it makes it invalid? Okay, that's a question
on us, there's a, you know, I could think of a lot
of answers, but it's an equal question on you. Why all of
a sudden do you want to pick on our idea of four
טפחים tefachim and think it's relevant to our position? So he says
ואמינא להו אנא, ve'amina lehu ana, I said back to them, האי
מאי? hai mai? What type of a point is that, trying to
turn the question back on me? בשלמא לדידי, bishlama ledidi, for me
it makes sense, דאמינא ארבע אמות, de'amina arba amot, I said four
אמות, amot, why? משום שיעורא דלאו שיעורא הוא, mishum shiura d'lav shiura
hu, because that's just, you know, the size. In any area of
הלכה halacha you have things that have minimum sizes and you don't
mix and match, like we just got through learning יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, and you don't say that a little bit less than a
ככותבת k'kotevet of food and a little bit less than a מלא
לוגמיו m'lo lugmav of liquid they should combine because one is stronger
and the other is weaker, so you should combine them. If they're
different types of things, they have different sizes and you don't combine
the two. So fine, you don't say oh it's stronger and let
it do the same work. Okay, so that's, so that's why the
air doesn't combine with the פסול סכך. pasul sechach. But why is
it a challenge to you?
כיון דלא שוו שיעורייהו להדדי, keivan d'lo shavu shiureihu lahadei, since they
don't have the same measure, one goes by four אמות amot and
one goes by three
טפחים, tefachim, לא מצטרפי, lo mitztarfi, they don't combine. You don't take
a little air and say air is stronger than פסול סכך pasul
sechach and we'll combine it to the פסול סכך. pasul sechach. They're
different. אלא לדידכו, ela ledidchu, but according to you, דאמרתון שיעורא משום
הפלגה, de'amritun shiura mishum haflaga, you said because here's the point. Where
did you get the idea of four טפחים? tefachim? This is what's
fascinating. The idea of four טפחים tefachim of פסול סכך pasul sechach
is not said in any משנה. mishnah. It comes out of the
בית מדרש beit midrash of רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. It's not
in any earlier source. So he says, where do you get the
idea that four טפחים tefachim should be a problem? Because four טפחים
tefachim normally defines, if you remember we've used four טפחים tefachim before,
it defines like a, a space, like the smallest רשות reshut you
have on שבת Shabbat is four טפחים tefachim by four טפחים tefachim
with, you know, with מחיצות mechitzot around. So it must be you
just learned logically, it's not like you have an arbitrary quantity that's
just sort of that's the way it is, x amount. You are
doing it by a logic. And what's the logic? The logic is
that once you have four טפחים, tefachim, then that's a whole space
unto itself. So you just argued logically, if that's a space unto
itself, it breaks up the continuity. So it's not like this idea
of x amount of stuff. Conceptually it's about creating a break, creating
a space to itself. So he says if it's about creating a
space to itself, then I've got my question. Then three טפחים tefachim
of פסול סכך pasul sechach should combine with two טפחים tefachim of
air because then it's the same idea, it's distancing, it's creating a
break. If it's a question of x amount
invalidates, right, okay, so that is a, that is like a certain
arbitrary quantity and it's x amount of this and y amount of
that and you don't mix and match. But he's saying this isn't
like x amount of this type of stuff and y of that.
Here it's an idea that a certain type, once you get to
four טפחים, tefachim, because you, again, you came up with this on
your own, so the logic has to be that that just creates
a lack of continuity and creates a break. So if it creates
a break, why can't a combination of פסול סכך pasul sechach and
air also create a break?
That's what the תלמוד Talmud means by משום הפלגה. mishum haflaga. Right.
הפלגה haflaga meaning
חילק, chilek, right. So let's read that again. So for me it's
an arbitrary question of x amount of this, y amount of that,
you don't combine quantities of different things. אלא לדידכו, ela ledidchu, but
according to you, דאמרתון שיעורא משום הפלגה, de'amritun shiura mishum haflaga,
you came up with this number not because there was some like
arbitrary amount mentioned in a משנה, mishnah, you need a certain amount.
You figured it out on your own and you decided, not you,
רב Rav and שמואל, Shmuel, and decided that it was because it
was creating a separation between the two halves of סכך. sechach, Once
you have four טפחים, tefachim, that separates the two spaces. If that's
what, if it's about separating, מה לי הפליג בסכך פסול מה לי
הפליג באויר. ma li hiflig be'sechach pasul ma li hiflig be'avir. If
that's what, if it's about separating, מה לי פליג בסכך פסול מה
לי פליג בסכך פסול ואויר? mah li palig be-schach pasul mah li
palig be-schach pasul ve-avir? Who cares? You once the two halves of
the סכך sechach. are separated by four טפחים, tefachim, who cares what's
in the middle? Let it be all סכך פסול, schach pasul let
it be a mix of סכך פסול schach pasul and אויר, avir,
still there's a reality that this half is separated from that half
by four טפחים, tefachim, okay? Again, so now it's quite fascinating, right
how he's presenting these two things and sort of honing in on
what the different conceptual model is, one is a quantity that invalidates
and the other is the reality of lack of continuity, and if
it's the reality of the distance between the two, who cares if
some of that is אויר. avir. Now the answer could be no,
because as long as some of it is אויר avir but not
too much, it kicks in the principle of לבוד lavud and makes
the אויר avir go away. That would be the logical answer, right?
You're saying look, you have a four טפח tefach gap, I'm saying
no, לבוד lavud disappears the gap, and לבוד lavud makes it only
a three טפח tefach gap. לבוד lavud imagines that you're going ahead
and fill that up. That's the obvious answer, but his question still
is if it's based on a gap, it should be a gap
with a combination of סכך פסול schach pasul and אויר avir should
also work.
So מחלוקת, machloket, it's a מחלוקת machloket about mode of thinking, qualitative
or
quantitative. Conceptual, quantitative about the שיעור shiur that's קובע koveia or the
quality of whether there's a break or it's continuous.
Exactly, exactly, although I wouldn't say it's right, it's about a way
you think, it's a way of thinking about this problem.
Yeah, okay, right. Okay, so אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, so
אביי Abaye said back to רבא, Rava, אביי Abaye was רבא's Rava
student. It's very interesting, you get like a whole interesting discussion of
different generations of אמוראים Amoraim here, רב ושמואל, Rav u-Shmuel, then you
have רבא, Rava, then you have אביי Abaye his student. You have
this language of אשכחינהו ויתבי
וקאמרי
ashkachinhu ve-yashvi ve-ka-amri
right, exactly.
So אביי Abaye said to רבא, Rava, ולמר נמי האי דלא שוו
שיעורייהו בסוכה גדולה, u-le-mar nami hai de-lo shavu shi'ureihu be-sukkah gedolah, he
says okay according to you it's true that in a big סוכה
sukkah you know there's not, you said I'm not going to combine
אויר avir with סכך פסול schach pasul because they have different measures,
because for me it's a quantity thing, so it's four אמות amot
and three טפחים, tefachim, and you don't combine even you know even
the stronger one doesn't combine with the weaker one. But says but
look according to you even though in a big סוכה sukkah they
go by different amounts, four אמות amot and three טפחים, tefachim, בסוכה
קטנה מי לא שוו שיעורייהו? be-sukkah ketanah mi lo shavu shi'ureihu? In
a small סוכה sukkah they have the same amount. Now what does
that mean? Right, why would רבא Rava say all of a sudden
that in a small סוכה, sukkah, a small סוכה sukkah means a
minimum size סוכה, sukkah, שבעה טפחים על שבעה טפחים. shiv'ah tefachim al
shiv'ah tefachim. Why would he say that all of a sudden now
it goes by three טפחים tefachim of פסול סכך? pasul schach? Like
that's what אביי Abaye is saying, אביי Abaye is saying to you
ah but in, why can't you combine them in a small
סוכה sukkah they do have similar measures and that should give a
basis for being allowing you to combine פסול סכך pasul schach with
אויר avir in other scenarios. So what's the similar measure in a
small סוכה? sukkah? It's three טפחים tefachim of אויר avir would be
a problem, why would I say all of a sudden three טפחים
tefachim of פסול סכך? pasul schach? It's true you don't even have
four אמות, amot, the whole thing is only שבעה טפחים, shiv'ah tefachim,
but where would you get the idea of three טפחים tefachim of
פסול סכך pasul schach would be a problem? So רש"י Rashi says
and again this is like coming out of thin air, excuse the
pun. If you look about ten lines down in the narrow lines,
בסוכה קטנה be-sukkah ketanah רש"י Rashi says, ששיעורה מצומצם מי לא שוו
שיעורייהו, she-shi'urah metzumtzam mi lo shavu shi'ureihu, aren't the שיעורים shiurim the
same? על כרחך אחד זה ואחד זה פסול בג' טפחים, al karchach
echad zeh ve-echad zeh pasul be-gimel tefachim, you have to admit that
in the small סוכה sukkah the פסול סכך pasul schach is even
three טפחים tefachim a problem, why? דכיון דנפיק מתורת לבוד, de-keivan de-nafik
mi-torat lavud, once it's no longer לבוד, lavud, חשיב chashiv it's significant
enough לבצוריה לשיעוריה דסוכה, le-vatzurei le-shi'urei de-sukkah, to say that it's a
to say that the סוכה sukkah has a smaller size if the
whole thing is a minimum size, once you have a certain amount
of פסול סכך pasul schach it's like it's not even a full
size
סוכה. sukkah. וכיון דשוו שיעורייהו לעניין שם סוכה ליתסרו, ve-keivan de-shavu shi'ureihu
le-inyan shem sukkah litsaru, and since there's a סוכה sukkah where it's
measured by the same amount you should always be able to combine
them even in a big סוכה. sukkah. But it's very strange where
he gets this idea that of course it's obvious that in a
small סוכה sukkah three טפחים tefachim of פסול סכך pasul schach would
be a problem. רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel actually I don't understand how
he reads the logic of the גמרא, Gemara, but he has אביי
Abaye saying wouldn't you admit that in a small סוכה sukkah four
טפחים tefachim of פסול סכך pasul schach is a problem, not four
אמות. amot. Now you can tell me why four טפחים tefachim of
פסול סכך pasul schach would be a problem in a small סוכה.
sukkah. Why would four טפחים? tefachim? Normally it's four אמות. amot. In
a small סוכה sukkah אביי Abaye says there four טפחים tefachim would
be a problem, why?
Because if it's seven by seven and four טפחים tefachim is פסול
סכך pasul schach then the majority is פסול סכך. pasul schach. Okay
but that's like a trick, that's not because it's a שיעור shiur
of four טפחים, tefachim, that's because it just works out to be
the majority. Okay but anyway that's what רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel says
which makes a little more sense, for some reason the our flow
of the גמרא Gemara is the way רש"י Rashi is reading it,
he's basically saying oh of course you got to admit by small
סוכה sukkah it's three טפחים. tefachim. So I don't know why he
has to admit that but okay that's his argument. So let's see
what he answers. So he says, אמר ליה התם לאו משום דשוו
שיעורייהו להדדי הוא, amar lei hatam lav mishum de-shavu shi'ureihu le-hadadi hu,
there it's not because they in principle have the same amount that
one is three that they all of a sudden the formal quantitative
amount is
three
טפחים, tefachim, אלא משום דליתיה. ella mishum de-leiteih. Right, but רש"י Rashi
is saying that
that's also his response to אביי. Abaye. His response to אביי Abaye
is it's not that in principle that's the size, it just works
out that way, right? Meaning it's not like there's a הלכה halacha
in a big סוכה sukkah four אמות amos is פסול, pasul, in
a small סוכה sukkah three טפחים tefachim פסול. pasul, That's not the
point. How much סכך פסול schach pasul in a small סוכה sukkah
is also four אמות, amos, but it happens to work out that
if once you have three טפחים tefachim of פסול סכך, pasul schach,
you can't consider that section to be included in the size of
the סוכה sukkah and therefore it works out that you don't have
a right size סוכה, sukkah, but it's not that it's directly functioning
as invalid סכך. schach So it works out that three טפחים tefachim
creates a problem, but it's not that that's the measure of פסול
סכך pasul schach in a small סוכה. sukkah. So fundamentally these are
two things that are never measured in the same way, סכך פסול
skach pasul is always four אמות, amos, air is always three טפחים,
tefachim, and therefore you can't combine them. But my argument to the
רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel approach is if it's not about a
quantitative measure, if it's about creating a break, then you should be
able to create a break with a combination of פסול סכך pasul
schach and air. Yes.
Well, to take this to its extreme you could have a seven
by seven סוכה sukkah but if you didn't, if you weren't worried
about this, you could conceivably have slightly more about
you could have nothing but פסול סכך pasul schach because you could
have four טפחים tefachim or you could have just one by little
more than one by one טפח tefach surrounded by air, and it's
silly.
Right, so that's basically the point. Yes. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says like this. So okay. So the גמרא Gemara says the following.
Okay. דכל היכא דלא שוו שיעורא להדדי לא מצטרפי, de-chol heicha de-lo
shavvu shiura le-hadadi lo mitztarfi, is that really true that you can't
combine what I'll call weaker and stronger things when they don't have
the same שיעור, shiur, right, like the example I gave you, right,
we sort of tend to assume that is true, you don't combine
food and drink on יום כיפור Yom Kippur even if one of
them has a smaller שיעור shiur than the other. You don't say
oh this is stronger and that's weaker and let's combine them. But
the גמרא Gemara says maybe there are some times we do that.
והתנן ve-ha-tnan and here we taught, it's amazing how much of טהרות
Taharos comes up in מסכת סוכה. Masechet Sukkah. הבגד שלשה על שלשה.
ha-beged sheloshah al sheloshah. How much is a minimum size a piece
of clothing in order to become טמא? tamei? So it's three טפחים
tefachim by three טפחים, tefachim, about nine inches by nine inches, then
it's considered to be a vessel and usable and so on. השק
ha-sak if it's sackcloth, ארבעה על ארבעה arba'ah al arba'ah has to
be bigger because it's not as quality of a material and therefore
only more of it is significant and once it's less than that
you throw it away, four by four טפחים. tefachim. העור ha-or leather,
חמשה על חמשה, chamishah al chamishah, five by five טפחים. tefachim. That's
fascinating because leather is more expensive, but maybe again you don't use
smaller pieces of leather. מפץ mapatz and if it's a mat like
made of reed, ששה על ששה shishah al shishah and we saw
that before, six טפחים tefachim by six טפחים. tefachim. So these are
the amount of sizes, the particular application, it could be for like
normal טומאה tumah but also for like if a זב zav sits
on it and one type of thing would be considered a minimum
to be a type of a seat, would also be a relevant
application. So so these are the different sizes. So let's say you
made a cushion with a combination of leather and cloth. How would
you measure it? Okay, so let's take a look. ותניא לה ve-tanya
lah we taught a ברייתא braisa on it, הבגד
והשק והעור והמפץ, ha-beged ve-ha-sak ve-ha-or ve-ha-mapatz, הבגד
והשק, ha-beged ve-ha-sak, השק והעור, ha-sak ve-ha-or, העור והמפץ, ha-or ve-ha-mapatz, if
you combined things on the list and according to the way רש"י
Rashi in one approach of תוספות Tosfos reads it, only contiguous things
because they're most similar, so if you combined cloth with sackcloth or
sackcloth with leather or leather with a mat, מצטרפין זה עם זה.
mitztarfin zeh im zeh. They do combine. Okay, now they combine like
the stricter one, but they combine. You basically have, it says that
a בגד, beged, right,
a
בגד beged is three טפחים, tefachim, okay, and what was it the
next one was the שק, sak, שק sak was four. So you
basically have three טפחים tefachim of שק, sak, okay, and one טפח
tefach of בגד. beged. So which is the stronger one, the one
that is more susceptible to טומאה, tumah, בגד beged or שק? sak?
בגד beged because a smaller amount of it is a problem, the
same way air is stronger because a smaller amount of air is
a problem whereas right סכך schach. is not. So let's use the
stronger בגד beged to fill out the measure and now that should
combine and the הלכה halacha is it does combine, that if a
שק sak will work for the last טפח, tefach, בגד beged will
work for the last טפח tefach as well. So that
is exactly what we say here, you can combine, use the stronger
one to fill up the שיעור shiur of the weaker one, and
it doesn't matter that they're separate שיעורין. shiurin. So let's use air
to fill up and complement the size of פסול סכך. pasul schach.
Wouldn't your point be made stronger if you had two
of...
Yeah, same way. Because he's saying it's רוב. rov.
It doesn't matter. No, in other words, that air adds up to
three.
No, no, no, but you can't do that. You can't use the
weaker thing to give you to give... no, you can't use... right,
it's only, it's exactly as I said, you can only use the
stronger one in place of the weaker one, not vice versa. Okay?
So סכך schach here would have done it, so you could replace
the סכך skach with בגד. beget. So פסול סכך pasul skach would
have created a problem, you could replace the פסול סכך pasul skach
with air. That would be the argument. So look, there are different
שיעורים shiurim and it works to combine them. So the גמרא Gemara
says no. התם כדיקתני טעמא, hatam kedeka tani taama, there's like we
explained the reason. אמר רבי שמעון: amar Rabbi Shimon: מה טעם? mah
taam? What allows us to combine them? הואיל וראוי לטמא מושב hoil
veraui letame moshav because they can combine in a particular type of
טומאה tumah when it comes to make a seat like something which
would be considered a seat of a זב. zav. כדתנן kedetnan like
we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, המקצע מכולן טפח על טפח, hamekatzea
mikullan tefach al tefach, if you took from any of these materials
and you cut out a square, a טפח tefach by a טפח,
tefach, טמא, tame, it is טמא. tame. So meaning they all do
share a size of טפח tefach by טפח tefach for one scenario,
the scenario of cutting out a perfect square טפח tefach by טפח.
tefach. Why? What's significance about that? What can you use that for?
טפח על טפח למאי חזי? tefach al tefach lemai chazi? What's it
fit for? So אמר ריש לקיש amar Reish Lakish משום רבי ינאי:
mishum Rabbi Yannai: הואיל וראוי
לטלאי hoil veraui letala'i or לטלו litlo אגב חמור, agab chamor, because
you can use it as a patch on a saddle seat. So
basically what it says is yeah, when you're trying to hold on
to these things as actual cloths or seats, they have different sizes.
But if you're cutting out a piece of a patch, all of
them cause to... are susceptible for טומאה tumah by one טפח tefach
by one טפח. tefach. All of them have significance at that size.
So since there is an area in הלכה halacha where these different
materials have the same size, or an area of relevant הלכה halacha
of טומאה tumah where they have the same size, that allows you
to combine them and to say well let the בגד beget do
the work, the stronger בגד beget do the work of the weaker
סכך skach because they're somewhat seen as in the same category because
at least in the area of making a patch, they have the
same size. But by סכך skach and air they never have the
same size and therefore you don't combine them, which is why אביי
Abaye wanted to create a scenario where they did have the same
size. Once we can find a case where they have the same
size, that would say you should be able to combine it. But
the answer is no, they're fundamentally separate categories, they cannot be combined.
These, which are fundamentally similar categories, the stronger one can do the
work of the weaker one. But that wouldn't work by סוכה. sukkah.
You would not say the stronger air to do the work of
the weaker סכך. skach Those are categorically different and they don't combine
air with סכך. skach. But again, that's if you're looking at it
quantitatively. His argument, רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel still is, but for
you guys it's about distance, you still have the reality of the
distance. And again, the most obvious answer is once it's less than
three טפחים, tefachim, that distance doesn't exist. That air is like it's
closed and that's why it's not a problem. Okay?
So yes, you've opened Pandora's box with טהרה, Tahara, I don't know,
it's a lot.
If one by one is good for a patch, then let it
be good for... then one by one should be the שיעור shiur
with the idea that if you cut it for a patch?
Right. So that you know, gets to the whole issue of כוונה
kavannah like we talked before about like when is a vessel considered
susceptible to טומאה? tumah? Like יורדין לידי מחשבה אין עולין אלא לידי
מעשה yordin liyedei machshavah ein olin ela liyedei ma'aseh if you remember
that. So if I... you have a piece of leather, is it
susceptible for טומאה? tumah? Well, if I'm going to use it
as a... you know, as a mat, and that's what I want
it to be used as, yes. If I'm not... if I'm going
to planning on making shoes out of it, the answer is no
because it's not yet complete. So my intention, right, determines whether this
is considered like a כלי kli or not, at what... you know,
what stage of development it is. So if you have a piece
of cloth or a piece of leather, you know, the normal usage
of that would be for like some type of a mat and
therefore it goes by certain minimum sizes. Once you intend to use
it as a patch, right, then it... then it changes its way
to categorize and therefore the quantity of things.
We talked about, you know, wood that doesn't yet have a בית
קיבול. beit kibul. Right. So but you're never intending it to use...
to have a בית קיבול. beit kibul. Why are we worried that
one day it'll have a base that... or you might think... Right?
We're not.
No, the גמרא... Gemara... you mean when it said that we're talking
about כלים משופים kelim meshupim and they tried to say that... yeah,
but the גמרא Gemara rejected that and that was only a... you
know, a דרבנן d'rabanan problem about סכך, skach. that wasn't a fundamental
טומאה tumah problem. For טומאה tumah to work... for something to be
susceptible for טומאה, tumah, it needs to have certain qualities, right? So
if it's wood, it has to have a בית קיבול, beit kibul,
other types of things it has to be a כלי, kli, it
has to be usable. And then there's the question about size. So
the basic point here is that in the standard case this stuff
is going to be used for something like a seat and therefore
the standard size is X, but in a case where it's כלי...
kli... be used as a patch, then the standard size switches. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this: ואמר רב חסדא. V'amar Rav
Chisda. Okay, so now we say, so בסורא Be-Sura אמרי להאי שמעתא
בהאי לישנא. amri lehai shemata behai lishna. In סורא Sura
they told over the discussion the way we just had it above.
Now סורא Sura was רב’s Rav’s ישיבה. yeshiva. So in סורא Sura
in רב’s Rav’s ישיבה—and yeshiva remember, it said that רבא Rabba found
the students in רב’s Rav’s ישיבה. yeshiva. So this whole version you
just read was the version that it was told over by the
students by רב’s Rav’s ישיבה, yeshiva, where רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel
were both saying the idea that ארבע אמות arba amot on the
side, דופן עקומה, dofen akuma, and ארבעה טפחים arba'ah tefachim in the
middle. That was a combined position of רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel.
That's how it was told over in רב’s Rav’s ישיבה. yeshiva. But
בנהרדעא, Be-Naharda’a, in נהרדעא, Naharda’a, which was whose ישיבה? yeshiva? Any guesses?
שמואל’s! Shmuel’s! מתנו, matnu, this is the way they said it. אמר
רב יהודה אמר שמואל. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel. No thing about
oh, רבא Rabba came in and bumped into the students in רב’s
Rav’s ישיבה. yeshiva. That's not the version they have in שמואל’s Shmuel’s
ישיבה. yeshiva. In שמואל’s Shmuel’s ישיבה, yeshiva, here’s the version that they
have: אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel. Says
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, סכך פסול
באמצע פוסל בארבעה. skach pasul be-emtza posel be-arba'ah. סכך skach, פסול pasul.
in the middle is ארבעה טפחים, arba'ah tefachim, מן הצד פוסל בארבע
אמות. min hatzad posel be-arba amot. From the side,
ארבע אמות. arba amot. So the same thing was said before in
the name of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel combined. Here it’s being
said in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, and it’s said also much
clearer, more directly, rather than the back and the forth. ארבעה טפחים
arba'ah tefachim in the middle, ארבע אמות arba amot at the edge
because of presumably דופן עקומה. dofen akuma. ורב אמר, V'Rav amar, and
according to this version, רב Rav says—and presumably this is רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda saying in the name of רב—רב says, בין מן הצד
בין באמצע בארבע אמות. bein min hatzad bein be-emtza be-arba amot.
According to this version, רב Rav has the position of רבא. Rabba.
רב Rav says whether the side, whether the middle, ארבע אמות. arba
amot. So it's a—still you have this debate. Everybody agrees ארבע אמות
arba amot on the side. That's the משנה. Mishna. What about the
middle? So according to the first version, רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel
said the middle ארבעה טפחים, arba'ah tefachim, רבא Rabba said the middle
ארבע אמות. arba amot. According to this, it's a debate of רב
Rav and
שמואל. Shmuel. שמואל Shmuel says ארבעה טפחים arba'ah tefachim in the middle,
רב Rav says even in the middle, ארבע אמות. arba amot. So
tomorrow we'll see them trying to prove it, not based on logic,
but based on textual proofs. But before we end, I want to
point your attention to a very fascinating רבנו חננאל. Rabbeinu Chananel. If
you look at רבנו חננאל, Rabbeinu Chananel, he says here,
if you take a look, it's like where is it? You see
like the last line of תוספות, Tosafot, go up from there about
ten lines, and the last word on the line of רבנו חננאל
Rabbeinu Chananel is בסורא. Be-Sura. Do you see where it says בסורא
Be-Sura on רבנו חננאל? Rabbeinu Chananel? So he says, בסורא מתנו הכי
אמרין. Be-Sura matnu hachi amrin. רבנו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel is on the
right-hand side. In סורא Sura it was like we said. אויר פוסל
בשלושה סכך פסול פוסל
בארבעה טפחים וכן הלכתא. Avir posel be-shlosha skach pasul posel be-arba'ah tefachim
ve-chen hilchata. ובפומבדיתא מתנו אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל. U-ve-Pumbedita matnu amar
Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel. So where our version says this is what
they taught in נהרדעא, Naharda'a, his version is this is what they
taught in
פומבדיתא. Pumbedita. Does anybody know whose ישיבה yeshiva פומבדיתא Pumbedita was? רב
יהודה! Rav Yehuda! רב Rav and שמואל’s Shmuel’s student. So our version
says in נהרדעא Naharda'a they taught, this is what רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda said in the name of שמואל. Shmuel. רבנו חננאל’s גרסא Rabbeinu
Chananel’s girsa was that's what they were teaching in פומבדיתא, Pumbedita, which
was רב יהודה’s ישיבה! Rav Yehuda’s yeshiva! So בפומבדיתא Be-Pumbedita they're teaching
what רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said in the name of שמואל. Shmuel.
So רב יהודה אמר שמואל Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel right bridges the
ישיבה yeshiva of פומבדיתא, Pumbedita, which is רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, and
the אמר שמואל, amar Shmuel, which is נהרדעא. Naharda'a. So it's quite
fascinating that in our version, this is what נהרדעא Naharda'a said, whereas
in his version, this is what they said in the ישיבה yeshiva
of פומבדיתא. Pumbedita. But either way, in רב’s Rav ישיבה, yeshiva, רב
Rav said ארבע אמות, arba amot, ארבעה טפחים arba'ah tefachim in the
middle, it was a combined רב Rav’s and שמואל Shmuel position. In
the רב יהודה אמר שמואל Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel version, it was
saying no, that is a debate of רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel.
רב Rav says ארבע אמות, arba amot, שמואל Shmuel says ארבעה טפחים.
arba'ah tefachim. Okay, more on this tomorrow.
This הוי אמינא hava amina with these swaths of cloth for a
זב zav and a זבה zava or a נדה niddah that they
actually got stained
because they were—no, it's not about stained, it's
about—any last מנחה?
mincha? דאוון daven in the shul
downstairs?
Mazel tov! Sent out a save the
date.
For the second month?
Oh, it means they're getting to the next
day.
Not a
number two
girl.
רבנו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom would not be
pleased.
Never have too many good
lists.